[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
gravity gravity is a rather special
force it's unusual it has different than
electrical forces magnetic forces and
it's connected in some way with
geometric properties of space space and
time but before and that connection is
of course the general theory of
relativity
before we start tonight for the most
part we will not be dealing with the
general theory of relativity we will be
dealing with gravity in its oldest and
simplest mathematical form well perhaps
not the oldest and simplest but
Newtonian gravity and going a little
beyond what Newton certainly nothing
that Newton would not have recognized or
couldn't have grasped Newton could grasp
anything but some ways of thinking about
it which will not be found in Newton's
actual work but still lutonium gravity
the Toney and gravity set up in a way
that that is useful for going on to the
general theory ok let's begin with
Newton's equations the first equation of
course is F equals MA force is equal to
mass times acceleration let's assume
that we have a frame of reference a
frame of reference that it means a set
of coordinates and as a collection of
clocks and those frame and that frame of
reference is what is called an inertial
frame of reference an inertial frame of
reference simply means 1 which if there
are no objects around to exert forces on
a particular let's call it a test object
a test object is just some object a
small particle or anything else that we
use to test out the various fields force
fields that might be acting on it the
inertial frame is one which when there
are no objects around to exert forces
that object will move with you
for motion with no acceleration that's
the idea of an inertial frame of
reference and so if you're an inertial
frame of reference and you have a pen
and you just let it go it stays there it
doesn't move if you give it a push
it will move off with uniform velocity
that's the idea of an inertial frame of
reference and in an inertial frame of
reference the basic Newtonian equation
number one I always forget which law is
which
there's Newton's first law second law
and third law I never can remember which
is which but they're all pretty much
summarized by f equals mass times
acceleration this is a vector equation I
expect people know what a vector is a
three vector equation will come later to
four vectors where when space and time
are united into space time but for the
moment space is space and time is time
and a vector means a thing which is like
a pointer in a direction in space as a
magnitude and that has components so
component by component the X component
of the force is equal to the mass of the
object times the X component of
acceleration Y component Z component and
so forth in order to indicate that
something is a vector equation I'll try
to remember to put an arrow over vectors
the mass is not a vector the mass is
simply a number every particle has a
mass every object has a mass and in
Newtonian physics the mass is conserved
that does not change now of course the
mass of this cup of coffee here can
change it's lighter now but it only
changes because mass has been
transported from one place to another so
you can change the mass of an object by
whacking off a piece of it and but if
you don't change the number of particles
change the number of molecules and so
forth then the mass is a conserved
unchanging quantity
so that's first equation now let me
write that in another form the other
form we imagine we have a coordinate
system an X a Y and a Z I don't have
enough directions on the blackboard to
draw Z I won't bother
there's x y and z sometimes we just call
them x1 x2 and x3 I guess I can draw it
in x3 is over here someplace XY and Z
and a particle has a position which
means it has a set of three coordinates
sometimes we will summarize the
collection of the three coordinates x1
x2 and x3
incidentally x1 and x2 and x3
are components of a vector the
components they are components of the
position vector of the particle position
vector of the particle I will often call
either small R or large are depending on
on the particular context R stands for
radius but the radius simply means the
distance between a point and the origin
for example we're really talking now
about a thing with three components XY
and Z and it's the radial vector the
radial vector this is the same thing as
the components of the vector R alright
the acceleration is a vector that's made
up out of the time derivatives of XY and
Z or X 1 X 2 and X 3 so for each
component the compose for each component
one two or three the acceleration which
let me indicate well let's just call it
a the acceleration is just equal the
components of it are equal to the second
derivatives of the coordinates with
respect to time
that's what acceleration is
the first derivative of position is
called velocity we can take this to be
component by component x1 x2 and x3 the
first derivatives velocity the second
derivative is acceleration we can write
this in vector notation I won't bother
but we all know what we mean I hope we
all know we mean buddies by acceleration
and velocity and so Newton's equations
are then summarized and summarized but
rewritten as the force on an object
whatever it is component by component is
equal to the mass times the second
derivative of the component of position
so that's the summary of I think it's
Newton's first and second law I can
never remember which they are Newton's
first law of course is simply the
statement that if there are no forces
then there's no acceleration that's
Newton's first law equal and opposite
right so this summarizes both the first
and second law I never understood why
there was a first and second law it
seems to me there was just one F equals
MA all right now let's begin even even
previous to Newton with Galilean gravity
gravity as Galileo understood it
actually I'm not sure how much of this
mathematics Galileo did or didn't
understand he certainly knew what
acceleration was he measured it I don't
know that he had thee but he certainly
didn't have calculus but he knew what
acceleration was so what Galileo studied
was the motion of objects in the
gravitational field of the earth in the
approximation that the earth is flat now
Galileo knew the earth wasn't flat but
he studied gravity in the approximation
where you never moved very far from the
surface of the earth and if you don't
move very far from the surface of the
earth you might as well take the surface
of the earth to be flat
and the significance of that is to
twofold first of all the direction of
gravitational forces is the same
everywhere as this is not true of course
if the earth is curved then gravity will
point toward the center but in the flat
space approximation gravity points down
down everywhere is always in the same
direction and second of all perhaps a
little bit less obvious but nevertheless
true then the approximation where the
earth is Infinite and flat goes on and
on forever infinite and flat the
gravitational force doesn't depend on
how high you are same gravitational
force here as here the implication of
that is that the acceleration of gravity
since force apart from the mass of an
object the acceleration on an object is
independent the way you put it and so
Galileo either did or didn't realize
well he again I don't know exactly what
Galileo did or didn't know but what he
said was equivalent to saying that the
force on an object in the flat space
approximation is very simple its first
of all has only one component pointing
downward if we take the upward sense of
things to be positive then we would say
that the force is let's just say the
component of the force in the X 2
direction the vertical Direction is
equal to minus the minus simply means
that the force is downward and it's
proportional to the mass of the object
times a constant called the
gravitational acceleration now the fact
that it's constant
Everywhere's in other words mass times G
doesn't vary from place to place that's
this fact that gravity doesn't depend on
where you are in the flat space
approximation
but the fact that the force is
proportional to the mass of an object
that is not obvious in fact for most
forces it's not true for electric forces
the force is proportional to the
electric charge not to the mass and so
gravitational forces are rather special
the strength of the gravitational force
on an object is proportional to its mass
that characterizes gravity almost
completely that's the special thing
about gravity the force is proportional
itself to the mass well if we combine F
equals MA
with the force law this is the law force
then what we find is that mass times
acceleration the second X now this is
the vertical component by DT squared is
equal to minus that's the minus M G
period that's it now the interesting
thing that happens in gravity is that
the mass cancels out from both sides
that is what's special about gravity the
mass cancels out from both sides and the
consequence of that is that the motion
of an object its acceleration doesn't
depend on the mass it doesn't depend on
anything about the particle a particle
object I'll use the word particle I
don't necessarily mean the point the
small particle or baseb as a particle an
eraser is a particle a piece of chalk is
a particle that the motion of the object
doesn't depend on the mass of the object
or anything else the result of that is
that if you take two objects of quite
different mass and you drop them they
fall exactly the same way our Galileo
did that experiment I don't know if
they're whether he really threw
something off the Leaning Tower of Pisa
or not it's not important he yeah he did
balls down an inclined plane
I don't know whether he actually did or
didn't I know the the the myth is that
he didn't die I find it very difficult
to believe that he didn't I've been in
Pisa last week I was in Pisa and I took
a look at the Leaning Tower of Pisa
galileo was born and lived in Pisa he
was interested in gravity how it would
be possible that he wouldn't think of
dropping something off the Leaning power
tower is beyond my comprehension you
look at that tower and you say that I
was good for one thing dropping things
off now I don't know maybe the Doge or
whoever they call the guy at the time
said no no Galileo you can't drop things
from the tower you'll kill somebody so
maybe he didn't but he must have surely
thought of it all right
so the result had he done it and had he
not had to worry about such spurious
effects as air resistance would be that
a cannonball and a feather would fall in
exactly the same way independent of the
mass and the equation would just say the
acceleration would first of all be
downward that's the minus sign and equal
to this constant G excuse me that mean
yes now G is a number it's 10 meters per
second per second at the surface of the
earth at the surface of the Moon it's
something smaller and the surface of
Jupiter it's something larger so it does
depend on the mass of the planet but the
acceleration doesn't depend on the mass
of the object you're dropping it depends
on the mass of the object you're
dropping it onto but not the mass of the
object that's dropping that fact that
gravitational motion is completely
independent the mass is called or it's
the simplest version of something that's
called the equivalence principle why
it's called the equivalence principle
we'll come to later what's equivalent to
what at this stage we could just say
gravity is equivalent between all
different objects independent of their
mass but that is not exact
were the equivalents an equivalence
principle was about that has a
consequence an interesting consequence
supposing they take some object which is
made up out of something which is very
unwritten just a collection of point
masses maybe maybe let's even say that
not even they're not even exerting any
forces on each other it's a cloud a
varied a few diffuse cloud of particles
and we watch it fall let's suppose we
start each particle from rest not all at
the same height and we let them all fall
some particles are heavy some particles
are light some of them may be big some
of them may be small how does the whole
thing fall the answer is all of the
particles fall at exactly the same rate
the consequence of it is that the shape
of this object doesn't deform as it
falls it stays absolutely unchanged the
relationship between the neighboring
parts are unchanged there are no
stresses or strains which tend to deform
the object so even if the object were
held together by some sort of struts or
whatever there would be no forces on
those struts because everything falls
together the consequence of that is the
falling in a gravitational field is
undetectable you can't tell that you're
falling in a gravitational field by you
when I say you can't tell certainly you
can tell the difference between freefall
and standing on the earth that's not the
point the point is that you can't tell
by looking at your neighbors or anything
else that there's a force being exerted
on you and that that force that's being
exerted on you is pulling you down word
you might as well for all practical
purposes be infinitely far from the
earth with no gravity
at all and just sitting there because as
far as you can tell there's no tendency
for the gravitational field to deform
this object or anything else you cannot
tell the difference between being in
free space infinitely far from anything
with no forces and falling freely in a
gravitational field
that's another statement of the
equivalence principle for example these
particles could be equipped with lasers
lasers and optical detectives of some
sort what's that oh you could certainly
tell if you was standing on the floor
here you could tell that something was
falling toward you but the question is
from within this object by itself
without looking at the floor without
knowing the floor was it well you can't
tell whether you're falling and it's
yeah yeah if there was something that
was calm that was not falling it would
only be because there was some other
force on it like a beam or a tower of
some sort of holding it up why because
this object if there are no other forces
on and only the gravitational forces it
will fall at the same rate as this all
right so that's another expression of
the equivalence principle that you
cannot tell the difference between being
in free space far from any gravitating
object versus being in a gravitational
field that we're going to modify this
this is of course it's not quite true in
a real gravitational field but in this
flat space approximation where
everything moves together you cannot
tell that there's a gravitational field
or at least you cannot tell the
difference I will not without seeing the
floor in any case the self-contained
object here does not experience anything
different than it would experience far
from any gravitating
hating object standing still or uniform
in uniform motion no you're accelerating
if you go up to the top of a high
building and you close your eyes and you
step off and go into freefall you will
feel exactly the same you feel weird I
mean that's not the way you usually feel
because your stomach will come up and
you know do some funny things you know
you might you might lose it but uh but
the point is you would feel exactly the
same discomfort in outer space
far from any gravitating object just
standing still you feel exactly the same
peculiar feelings one of those peculiar
feelings due to they're not due to
falling they do to not fall well they do
to the fact that when you stand on the
earth here there are forces on the
bottoms of your feet which keep you from
falling and if the earth suddenly
disappeared from under my feet sure
enough my feet would feel funny because
they used to having those forces exerted
on their bottoms you get it
I hope so the fact that you feel funny
in freefall is because you're not used
to freefall and it doesn't matter
whether you're infinitely far from any
gravitating object standing still or
freely falling in the presence of a
gravitational field now as I said this
will have to be modified in a little bit
there are such things as tidal forces
those tidal forces are due to the fact
that the earth is curved and that the
gravitational field is not the same in
every same direction in every point and
that it varies with height that's due to
the finiteness of the earth but in the
flat space surprise and the Flat Earth
approximation where the earth is
infinitely big pulling uniformly
there is no other effective gravity that
is any different than being in free
space okay again that's known as the
equivalence principle now let's go on
beyond the flat space or the Flat Earth
approximation and move on to Newton's
theory of gravity Newton's theory of
gravity says every object in the
universe exerts a gravitational force on
every other object in the universe let's
start with just two of them equal and
opposite attractive attractive means
that the direction of the force on one
object is toward the other one equal and
opposite forces and the magnitude of the
force the magnitude of the force of one
object on another let's let's
characterize them by a mass let's call
this one little m think of it as a
lighter mass and this one which we can
imagine as a heavier object will call it
begin all right Newton's law of force is
that the force is proportional to the
product of the masses making either mass
heavier will increase the force or the
product of the masses begin tons of
little m
inversely proportional to the square of
the distance between them let's call
that R squared let's call the distance
between them are and there's a numerical
constant this for this law by itself
could not possibly be right it's not
dimensionally consistent the if you work
out the dimensions of force mass mass
and R will not dimensionally consistent
there has to be a numeric
constant in there and that numerical
constant is called capital G Newton's
constant and it's very small it's a very
small constant I'll write down what it
is G it is equal to six or six point
seven roughly times 10 to the minus 11th
which is a small number so in the face
of it it seems that gravity is a very
weak force you might not think that
gravity is such a weak force but to
convince yourself it's a weak force
there's a simple experiment that you can
do week week by comparison with other
forces I've done this for car classes
and you can do it yourself just take an
object hanging by a string and two
experiments the first experiment take a
little object here and electrically
charge it electrically charge it by
rubbing it on your sweater that doesn't
put very much electric charge on it but
it charges it up enough to feel some
electrostatic force and then take
another object of exactly the same kind
rub it on your shirt and put it over
here what happens they repel and the
fact that they repel means that this
string will shift and you'll see a shift
take another example take your little
ball there to be iron and put a magnet
next to it again you'll see quite an
easily detectable deflection of the of
the string holding it next
take a 10,000 pound weight and put it
over here guess what happens
undetectable you cannot see anything
happen the gravitational force is much
much weaker than most other kinds of
forces and that's due to the or not due
to but the not due to that the fact that
it's so weak is encapsulated in this
small number here another way to say it
is if you take two masses each of one
kilometer not one kilometer one kilogram
kilogram is a good healthy mass right
nice chunk of iron mm and you separate
them by one meter then the force between
them is just G and it's six point seven
times ten to the minus eleven the you
know the units being Newtons so it's
very very weak force but weak as it is
we feel that rather strenuously we feel
it strongly because the earth is so darn
heavy so the heaviness of the earth
makes up for the smallness of G and so
we wake up in the morning feeling like
we don't want to get out of bed because
gravity is holding us down
Oh Oh the equal and opposite equal and
opposite that's the that's the rule
that's Newton's third law the forces are
equal and opposite so the force on the
large one due to the small one is the
same as the force of the small one on
the large one
and but it is proportional to the
product of the masses so the meaning of
that is I'm not heavier than I like to
be but but I'm not very heavy I'm
certainly not heavy enough to deflect
the hanging weight significantly but I
do exert a force on the earth which is
exactly equal and opposite to the force
that they're very heavy earth exerts on
me why does the earth excel if I dropped
from a certain height I accelerate down
the earth hardly accelerates at all even
though the forces are equal why is it
that the earth if the forces are equal
my force on the earth and the Earth's
force on me of equal why is it that the
earth accelerates so little and I
accelerate so much yeah because the
acceleration involves two things it
involves the force and the mass the
bigger the mass the less the
acceleration for a given force so the
earth doesn't accelerate quickly I think
it was largely a guess but there was
certain was an educated guess and what
was the key ah no no it was from
Kepler's it was from Kepler's laws it
was from Kepler's laws he worked out
roughly speaking I don't know exactly
what he did he was rather secretive and
he didn't really tell people what he did
but the piece of knowledge that he had
was Kepler's laws of motion planetary
motion and my guess is that he just
wrote down a general force
realized that he would get Kepler's laws
of motion for the inverse-square law I
don't believe he had any underlying
theoretical reason to believe in the
inverse-square law that's correct he
asked a question for inverse square laws
no no it wasn't the ellipse which was
the the the orbits might have been
circular it was the fact that the period
varies is the three halves power of the
radius all right the period of motion is
circular motion has an acceleration
toward the center any motion in the
circle is accelerated to the center if
you know the period in the radius then
you know the acceleration toward the
center okay or we could write let's
let's do it anybody know what if I know
the angular frequency the angular
frequency of going around in an orbit
that's called Omega you know a--they and
it's basically just the inverse period
okay
Omega is roughly the inverse period
number of cycles per second what's the
what is the acceleration of a thing
moving in a circular orbit anybody
remember Omega squared R Omega squared R
that's the acceleration now supposing he
sets that equal to some unknown force
law f of r and then divides by r then he
finds Omega as a function of the radius
of the orbit okay well let's do it for
the real case for the real case inverse
square law f of r is 1 over r squared so
this would be 1 over r cubed
and in that form it is Kepler's second
law remember which one it is it's the
law that says that the frequency or the
period the square of the period is
proportional to the cube of the radius
that was the law of Kepler so from
Kepler's laws he easily could have that
that one law he could easily deduce that
the force was proportional to 1 over R
squared I think that's probably
historically what what he did then on
top of that he realized if you didn't
have a perfectly circular orbit then the
inverse square law was the unique law
which would give which would give
elliptical orbits so who's to say
[Music]
well then of course there are the forces
on them for two objects are actually
touching each other there are all sorts
of forces between them that I'm not just
gravitational electrostatic forces
atomic forces nuclear forces so you'll
have to my breaks down yeah then it
breaks down when they get so close that
other important forces come into play
the other important forces for example
are the forces that are holding this
object and preventing it from falling
these we usually call them contact
forces but in fact what they really are
is various kinds of electrostatic for
electrostatic forces between the atoms
and molecules in the table in the atoms
and molecules in here so other kinds of
forces all right
incidentally let me just point out if
we're talking about other kinds of force
laws for example electrostatic force
laws then the force we still have F
equals MA but the force law the force
law will not be that the force is
somehow proportional to the mass times
something else but it could be the
electric charge if it's the electric
charge then electrically uncharged
objects will have no forces on them and
they won't accelerate electrically
charged objects will accelerate in an
electric field so electrical forces
don't have this Universal property that
everything falls or everything moves in
the same way uncharged particles move
differently than charged particles with
respect to electrostatic forces they
move the same way with respect to
gravitational forces and as a repulsion
and attraction whereas gravitational
forces are always attractive where
where's my gravitational force
I lost it yeah here is all right so
that's that's Newtonian gravity between
two objects for simplicity let's just
put one of them the heavy one at the
origin of coordinates and study the
motion of the light one then Oh
incidentally one usually puts let me let
me refine this a little bit as I've
written it here I haven't really
expressed it as a vector equation this
is the magnitude of the force between
two objects thought of as a vector
equation we have to provide a direction
for the force vectors have directions
what direction is the force on this
particle well the answer is its along
the radial direction itself so let's
call the radial distance R or the radial
vector R then the force on little m here
is along the direction R but it's also
opposite to the direction of R the
radial vector relative to the origin
over here points this way on the other
hand the force points in the opposite
direction if we want to make a real
vector equation out of this we first of
all have to put a minus sign that
indicates that the force is opposite to
the direction of the radial distance
here but we have to also put something
in which tells us what direction the
force is in it's along the radial
direction but wait a minute if I
multiply it by r up here I had better
divide it by another factor of R
downstairs to keep the magnitude
unchanged the magnitude of the force is
1 over R squared if I were to just
randomly come and multiply it by r that
would make the magnitude bigger by a
factor of our so I have to divide it by
the magnitude of our this is Newton's
force law expressed in vector form now
let's imagine that we have a whole
assembly of particles a whole bunch of
them they're all exerting forces on one
another in pairs they exert exactly the
force that Newton wrote down but what's
the total force on a particle let's
label these particles this is the first
one the second one the third one the
fourth one that I thought that thought
this is the ithe one over here so I is
running index which labels which
particle we're talking about the force
on the eigth article
let's call F sub I and let's remember
that it's a vector it's equal to the sum
now this is not an obvious fact that
when you have two objects exerting a
force on the third that the force is
necessarily equal to the sum of the two
forces of the two are of the two objects
you know what I mean
but it is a fact anyway obvious on how
obvious it is a fact that gravity does
work that way at least in the Newtonian
approximation with Einstein it breaks
down a little bit but in Newtonian
physics the force is the sum and so it's
a sum over all the other particles let's
write that J not equal to I that means
it's a sum over all not equal to I so
the force on the first particle doesn't
come from the first particle it comes
from the second particle third particle
fourth particle and so forth
each individual force involves M sub I
the
force of the ice particle times the four
times the mass of the Jade particle
product of the masses divided by the
square of the distance between them
let's call that R IJ squared the
distance between the eigth article his I
and J the distance between the earth
particle and the J particle is RI J but
then just as we did before we have to
give it a direction but a minus sign
here that indicates that it's attractive
another R IJ upstairs but that's a
vector R IJ and make this cube
downstairs alright so that says that the
force on the I've particle is the sum of
all the forces due to all the other ones
of the product of their masses inverse
square in the denominator and the
direction of each individual force on
this particle is toward the other all
right this is a vector sum yeah hmm the
minus indicates that it's attractive
excellent but you've got the vector
going from like a J oh let's see
that's a vector going from the J yes
there is a question of the sine of this
vector over here
so yeah you know absolutely let's yeah I
actually think it's yeah you're right
you're absolutely right the way I've
written that there should not be a minus
sign here all right but if I put our ji
there then there would be a minus sign
right so you're right but in any case
every one every one of the forces is
attractive and what we have to do is to
add them up we have to add them up as
vectors and so there's some resulting
vector some resultant vector which
doesn't point toward any one of them in
particular but points in some direction
which is determined by the vector sum of
all the others all right but the
interesting fact is if we combine this
this is the force on the earth particle
if we combine it with Newton's equations
let's combine it with Newton's equipped
with Newton's F equals MA equations then
this is F
this on the ice particle this is equal
to the mass of the I particle times the
acceleration of the ice particle again
vector equations now the sum here is
over all the other particles we're
focusing on number I I the mass of the
ice particle will cancel out of this
equation I don't want to throw it away
but let's just circle it and now put it
over on the side we notice that the
acceleration of the ice particle does
not depend on its mass again once again
because the mass occurs in both sides of
the equation it can be cancelled out and
the motion of the ayth particle does not
depend on the mass of the earth particle
it depends on the masses of all the
other ones all the other ones come in
but the mass of the iPart achill cancels
out of the equation so what that means
is if we had a whole bunch of particles
here and we added one more over here its
motion would not depend on the mass of
that particle it depends on the mass of
all the other ones but it doesn't depend
on the mass of the i particle here okay
that's again the equivalence principle
that the motion of a particle doesn't
depend on its mass and again if we had a
whole bunch of particles here if they
were close enough together they were all
moving the same way before before i
discuss lumo mathematics let's just
discuss tidal forces what tidal forces
are
once you set this whole thing into
motion dynamic young we have all
different masses and each part what's
going to be affected by each one is
every particle in there is going to
experience a uniform acceleration oh no
no no no no acceleration is not uniform
the acceleration will get larger when it
gets closer to one of the particles it
won't be uniform anymore it won't be
uniform now because the force is not
independent of where you are now the
force depends on where you are relative
to the objects that are exerting the
force it was only in the Flat Earth
approximation where the force didn't
depend on where you were okay now the
force varies so it's larger when you're
far away it's sorry it's smaller when
you're far away it's larger when you're
in close
it changes
in a vector form with each individual
particles each one of them is changing
position yeah
and and so is the dynamics that every
one of them is going towards the center
of gravity of the fire not necessarily I
mean they could be flying apart from
each other but they will be accelerating
toward each other okay if I throw this
eraser into the air with greater than
the escape velocity it's not going to
turn around and fall back
changing with what with respect to what
time oh it changes with respect to time
because the object moves moves further
and further away it's not uniformly the
radius is changing and it's yeah let's
take the earth here's the earth and we
drop a small mass from far away as that
mass moves in its acceleration increases
why does its acceleration increase the
deceleration increases because the
radial distance gets smaller so in that
sense it's not the alright now once the
gravitational force depends on distance
then it's not really quite true that you
don't feel anything in a gravitational
field you feel something which is to
some extent it different than you would
feel in free space without any
gravitational field the reason is more
or less obvious here you are his is the
earth now you're you or me or whoever it
is happens to be extremely tall
a couple of thousand miles tall well
this person's feet are being pulled by
the gravitational field more than his
head or another way of saying the same
thing is if let's imagine that the
person is very loosely held together
he's just more or less a gas of we are
pretty loosely held together at least I
am right all right
the acceleration on the lower portions
of his body are larger than the
accelerations on the upper portions of
his body so it's quite clear what
happens to her
he gets stretched he doesn't get a sense
of falling as such he gets a sense of
stretching being stretched feet being
pulled away from his head at the same
time let's uh let's all right so let's
change the shape a little bit I just
spend the week two weeks in Italy and my
shape changes whenever I go to Italy and
it tends to get more horizontal my head
is here my feet are here and now I'm
this way
still loosely put together right now
what well not only does the force depend
on the distance but it also depends on
the direction the force arm my left end
over here is this way the force on my
right end over here is this way the
force on the top of my head is down but
it's weaker than the force on my feet so
there are two effects one effect is to
stretch me vertically it's because my
head is not being pulled as hard as my
feet but the other effect is to be
squished horizontally by the fact that
the forces on the left end of me are
pointing slightly to the right and the
forces on the right end of me are
pointing slightly to the left
so a loosely knit person
like this falling in freefall near a
real planet or real gravitational object
which has a real Newtonian gravitational
field around it will experience a
distortion will experience a degree of
distortion and a degree of being
stretched vertically being compressed
horizontally but if the object is small
enough or small enough mean let's
suppose the object that's falling is
small enough if it's small enough then
the gradient of the gravitational field
across the size of the object will be
negligible and so all parts of it will
experience the same gravitational
acceleration all right so tidal for
these are tidal forces these forces
which tend to tear things apart
vertically and squish them this way
tidal forces tidal forces are forces
which are real you feel them I mean
certainly new the car the cause of the
tides yeah I don't know to what extent
he calculated what do you mean
calculated the well I doubt that he was
capable I'm not sure whether he
estimated the height of the of the
deformation of the oceans or not but I
think you did understand this much about
tides okay so that's the that's what's
called tidal force and then under the
tidal force has this effect of
stretching and in particular if we take
the earth just to tell you just to tell
you why it's called tidal forces of
course it's because it has to do with
tides I'm sure you all know the story
but if this is the moon down here then
the moon exerting forces on the earth
exerts tidal forces on the earth which
means to some extent that tends to
stretch it this way and squash it this
way well the earth is pretty rigid so it
doesn't it doesn't deform very much due
to due to these two
the moon but what's not rigid is the
layer of water around it and so the
layer of water tends to get stretched
and squeezed and so it gets deformed
into the a the form shell of water with
a bump on this side and the bump on that
side alright I'm not gonna go any more
deeply into that that I'm sure you've
all seen okay but let's define now what
we mean by the gravitational field the
gravitational field is abstracted from
this formula we have a bunch of
particles
[Music]
don't you have need some some coordinate
geometry so that would you have the four
kind of middle is being pulled by all
the other guys on the side I'm not
explaining it right it's always negative
is that what you're saying doesn't know
I'm saying so she's attractive all right
so you have but what about the other
guys that are pulling upon him a
different direction here and we're
talking about the force on this person
over here
obviously there's one force pressing
this pushing this way and another force
pushing that way okay no the cone no
they're all opposite to the direction of
the object which is pulling on
that's what this - sorry instead well
you kind of retracted the minus sign at
the front and reverse the ji yeah so
it's the trend we can get rid of a -
like a RI j and our ji are opposite to
each other one of them is the vector
between I and J I and J and the other
one is the vector from J to I so they're
equal and opposite to each other the
minus sign there look as far as the
minus sign goes all it means is that
every one of these particles is pulling
on this particle toward it as opposed to
pushing away from it it's just a
convention which keeps track of
attraction instead of repulsion
yeah for the for the ice master that's
my word you want to make sense but if
you can look at it as a kind of an in
Samba wasn't about a linear conic
component to it because the ice guy
affects the Jade guy and then put you
compute the Jade guy when you take it
yeah now what this what this formula is
for is supposing you know the positions
or all the others you know that then
what is the force on the one additional
one but you're perfectly right once you
let the system evolve then each one will
cause a change in motion and the other
one and so it becomes a complicated as
you say nonlinear mess but this formula
is a formula for if you knew the
position and location of every particle
this would be the force something you
need to solve some equations to know how
the particles move but if you know where
they are then this is the force on the
particle alright let's come to the idea
of the gravitational field the
gravitational field is in some ways
similar to the electric field of our of
an electric charge
it's the combined effect of all the
masses Everywhere's and the way you
define it is as follows you imagine an
one more particle one more particle
amount you can take it to be a very
light particle so it doesn't influence
the motion of the others and one more
particle in your imagination you don't
really have to add it in your
imagination and ask what the force on it
is the force is the sum of the forces
due to all the others it is proportional
each term is proportional to the mass of
the sec strip article this extra
particle which may be imaginary is
called a test particle it's the thing
that you're imagining testing out the
gravitational field with you take a
light little particle and you put it
here and you see how it accelerates
knowing how it accelerates tells you how
much force is on it in fact it just
tells you how it accelerates and you can
go around and imagine putting it in
different places and mapping out the
force field that's on that particle or
the acceleration field since we already
know that the force is proportional to
the mass then we can just concentrate on
the acceleration the acceleration all
particles will have the same
acceleration independent of the mass so
we don't even have to know what the mass
of the particle is we put something over
there a little bit of dust and we see
how it accelerates acceleration is a
vector and so we map out in space the
acceleration of a particle at every
point in space either imaginary or real
particle and that gives us a vector
field at every point in space every
point in space there is a gravitational
field of acceleration it can be thought
of as the acceleration you don't have to
think of it as force acceleration
the acceleration of a point mass located
at that position it's a vector it has a
direction it has a magnitude and it's a
function of position so we just give it
a name the acceleration due to all the
gravitating objects it's a vector and it
depends on position here X means
location it means all of the position
components of position XY and Z and it
depends on all the other masters in the
problem that is what's called the
gravitational field it's very similar to
the electric field except the electric
field and the electric field is force
per unit charge it's the force on an
object divided by the charge on the
object the gravitational field is the
force of their on the object divided by
the mass on the object since the force
is proportional to the mass the the
acceleration field doesn't depend on
which kind of particle we're talking
about all right so that's the idea of a
gravitational field it's a vector field
and it varies from place to place and of
course if the particles are moving it
also varies in time
if everything is in motion the
gravitational field will also depend on
time we can even work out what it is we
know what the force on the earth
particle is all right the force on a
particle is the mass times the
acceleration so if we want to find the
acceleration let's take the ayth
particle to be the test particle little
eye represents the test particle over
here let's erase the intermediate step
over here and write that this is in AI
times AI but let me call it now capital
a the acceleration of a particle at
position X
is given by the right hand side and we
can cross out BMI because it cancels
from both sides so here's a formula for
the gravitational field at an arbitrary
point due to a whole bunch of massive
objects a whole bunch of massive objects
an arbitrary particle put over here will
accelerate in some direction that's
determined by all the others and that
acceleration is the gravitation the
definition is the definition of the
gravitational field
ok let's um let's take a little break we
usually take a break in about this time
and I recover my breath to go on we need
a little bit of fancy mathematics we
need a piece of mathematics called
Gauss's theorem and Gauss's theorem
involves
integrals derivatives divergences and we
need to spell those things out there a
central part of the theory of gravity
and much of these things we've done in
the context of a lot of electrical
forces in particular the concept of
divergence divergence of a vector field
so I'm not going to spend a lot of time
on it if you need to fill in then I
suggest you just find any little book on
vector calculus and find out what a
divergence and a gradient and a curl
we don't do curl today what those
concepts are and look up Gauss's theorem
and they're not terribly hard but we're
gonna go through them fairly quickly
here since they we've done them several
times in the past right
imagine that we have a vector field
let's call that vector field a it could
be the field of acceleration and that's
the way I'm gonna use it well for the
moment it's just an arbitrary vector
field a it depends on position when I
say it's a field the implication is that
it depends on position now I probably
made it completely unreadable a of X
varies from point to point and I want to
define a concept called the divergence
of the field now it's called the
divergence because one has to do is the
way the field is spreading out away from
a point for example a characteristic
situation where we would have a strong
divergence for a field is if the field
was spreading out from a point like that
the field is diverging away from the
point incidentally if the field is
pointing inward then one might say the
field has a convergence but we simply
say it has a negative divergence
all right so divergence can be positive
or negative and there's a mathematical
expression which represents the degree
to which the field is spreading out like
that it is called the divergence I'm
going to write it down and it's a good
thing to get familiar with certainly if
you're going to follow this course it's
a good thing to get familiar with but
are they going to follow any kind of
physics course past freshman physics the
idea of divergence is very important all
right supposing the field a has a set of
components the one two and three
component but we could call them the x
y&z component now I'll use x y&z are
X Y & Z which I previously called X 1 X
2 and X 3 it has components X a X a Y
and a Z those are the three components
of the field
well the divergence has to do among
other things with the way the field
varies in space if the field is the same
everywhere as in space what does that
mean that would mean the field that has
both not only the same magnitude but the
same direction everywhere is in space
then it just points in the same
direction everywhere else with the same
magnitude
it certainly has no tendency to spread
out when does a field have a tendency to
spread out when the field varies for
example it could be small over here
growing bigger growing bigger growing
bigger and we might even go in the
opposite direction and discover that
it's in the opposite direction and
getting bigger in that direction then
clearly there's a tendency for the field
to spread out away from the center here
the same thing could be true if it were
varying in the vertical direction or who
are varying in the other horizontal
direction and so the divergence whatever
it is has to do with derivatives of the
components of the field I'll just tell
you exactly what it is it is equal to
the divergence of a field is written
this way upside down triangle and the
meaning of this symbol the meaning of an
upside down triangle is always that it
has to do with the derivatives the three
derivatives derivative whether it's the
three partial derivatives derivative
with respect to XY and Z and this is by
definition the derivative with respect
to X of the X component of a plus the
derivative with respect to Y of the Y
component of a plus the derivative with
respect to Z of the Z component of it
that's definition what's not a
definition is a theorem and it's called
Gauss's theorem no that's a scalar
quantity
that's a scalar quantity yeah it's a
scalar quantity so it's let me write it
it's the derivative of a sub X with
respect to X that's what this means plus
the derivative of a sub Y with respect
to Y plus the derivative of a sub Z with
respect to Z yes so the arrows you were
drawn over there those were just a on
the other board
you drew some arrows on the other board
that are now hidden yeah those were just
a and a has a divergence when it's
spreading out away from a point but that
there vergence is itself a scalar
quantity oh let me try to give you some
idea of what divergence means in a
context where you can visualize it
imagine that we have a flat lake alright
just the water thin a a shallow lake and
water is coming up from underneath it's
being pumped in from somewheres
underneath what happens that the water
is being pumped in of course it tends to
spread out let's assume that the height
let's assume the depth can't change we
put a lid over the whole thing so it
can't change its depth we pump some
water in from underneath and it spreads
out okay we suck some water out from
underneath
and it spreads in it anti spreads it has
so the spreading water has a divergence
water coming in toward the towards the
place where it's being sucked out it has
a convergence or a negative divergence
now we can be more precise about that we
look down at the lake from above and we
see all the water is moving of course
it's moving if it's being pumped in the
world it's moving and there is a
velocity vector at every point there is
a velocity vector so at every point in
this lake there's a velocity vector
vector and in particular if there's
water being pumped in from the center
here right underneath the bottom of the
lake there's some water being pumped in
the water will spread out away from that
point okay and there'll be a divergence
where the water is being pumped in okay
if the water is being pumped out then
exactly the opposite the the arrows
point inward and there's a negative
divergence the if there's no divergence
then for example a simple situation with
no divergence that doesn't mean the
water is not moving but a simple example
with no divergence is the waters all
moving together you know the river is
simultaneous the lake is all
simultaneously moving in the same
direction with the same velocity it can
do that without any water being pumped
in but if you found that the water was
moving to the right on this side and the
left on that side you'd be pretty sure
that somebody is in between water had to
be pumped in right if you found the
water was spreading out away from a line
this way here and this way here
then you'd be pretty sure that some
water was being pumped in from
underneath along this line here well you
would see it another way you would
discover that the X component of the
velocity has a derivative it's different
over here than it is over here the X
component of the velocity varies along
the x direction so the fact that the X
component of the velocity is varying
along the
direction there's an indication that
there's some water being pumped in here
likewise if you discovered that the
water was flowing up over here and down
over here you would expect that in here
somewhere as some water was being pumped
in
so derivatives of the velocity are often
an indication that the some water being
pumped in from underneath that pumping
in of the water is the divergence of the
velocity vector now the the the the
water of course is being pumped in from
underneath so there's a direction of
flow but it's coming from from
underneath there's no sense of direction
well okay that's that's what diverges
just the diagrams you already have on
the other board behind there you take
say the rightmost arrow and you draw a
circle between the head and tail in
between then you can see the in and out
the in arrow and the arrow of a circle
right in between those two and let's say
that's the bigger arrow is created by a
steeper slope of the street it's just
faster it's going fast it's going okay
and because of that there's a divergence
there that's basically it's sort of the
difference between that's right that's
right if we drew a circle around here or
we would see that more since the water
was moving faster over here than it is
over here more water is flowing out over
here then it's coming in over here where
is it coming from
it must be pumped in the fact that
there's more water flowing out on one
side then it's coming in from the other
side must indicate that there's a net
inflow from somewheres else
and the somewheres else would be from
the pump in water from underneath so
that's that's the idea of
oops could it also be because it's
thinning out with that be a crazy
example like the late guy young well
okay I took all right so let's be very
specific now I kept the lake having an
absolutely uniform height and let's also
suppose that the density of water water
is an incompressible fluid it can't be
squeezed it can't be stretched then the
velocity vector would be the right thing
to think about them yeah but you could
have no you're right you could have a
velocity vector having a divergence
because the water is not because water
is flowing in but because it's thinning
out yeah that's that's also possible
okay but let's keep it simple all right
and you can have the idea of a
divergence makes sense in three
dimensions just as well as two
dimensions you simply have to imagine
that all of space is filled with water
and there are some hidden pipes coming
in depositing water in different places
so that it's spreading out away from
points in three-dimensional space in
three-dimensional space this is the
expression for the divergence if this
were the velocity vector at every point
you would calculate this quantity and
that would tell you how much new water
is coming in at each point of space so
that's the divergence now there's a
theorem which the hint of the theorem
was just given by Michael there
it's called Gauss's theorem and it says
something intuitive very intuitively
obvious you take a surface any surface
take any surface
or any curve in two dimensions and now
suppose there's a vector field that the
field points now think of it as the flow
of water and now let's take the total
amount of water that's flowing out of
the surface obviously there's some water
flowing out over here and of course we
want to subtract the water that's
flowing in let's calculate the total
amount of water that's flowing out of
the surface that's an integral over the
surface why is it an integral because we
have to add up the flows of water
outward where the water is coming inward
that's just negative negative flow
negative outward flow we add up the
total outward flow by breaking up the
surface into little pieces and asking
how much flow is coming out from each
little piece yeah how much water is
passing out through the surface if the
water is incompressible incompressible
means density is fixed and furthermore
the depth of the water is being kept
fixed there's only one way that water
can come out of the surface and that's
if it's being pumped in if there's a
divergence the divergence could be over
here could be over here could be over
here could be over here in fact any ways
where there's a divergence will cause an
effect in which water will flow out of
this region yeah so there's a connection
there's a connection between what's
going on on the boundary of this region
how much water is flowing through the
boundary on the one hand and what the
divergence is in the interior the
connection between the two and that
connection is called Gauss's theorem
what it says is that the integral of the
divergence in the interior that's the
total amount of flow coming in from
outside from underneath the bottom of
the lake the total integrated and now by
integrated I mean in the sense of an
integral
the integrated amount of flow in that's
the integral of the divergence the
integral over the interior in the
three-dimensional case it would be
integral DX dy DZ over the interior of
this region of the divergence of a if
you like to think of a is the velocity
field that's fine is equal to the total
amount of flow that's going out through
the boundary and how do we write that
the total amount of flow that's flowing
outward through the boundary we break up
let's take the three-dimensional case we
break up the boundary into little cells
each little cell is a little area let's
call each one of those little areas D
Sigma these Sigma Sigma stands for
surface area Sigma is the Greek letter
Sigma it stands for surface area this
three-dimensional integral over the
interior here is equal to a
two-dimensional integral the Sigma over
the surface and it is just the component
of a perpendicular to the surface let's
call a perpendicular to the surface
D Sigma a perpendicular to the surface
is the amount of flow that's coming out
of each one of these little boxes notice
incidentally that if there's a flow
along the surface it doesn't give rise
to any fluid coming out it's only the
flow perpendicular to the surface the
component of the flow perpendicular to
the surface which carries fluid from the
inside to the outside
so we integrate the perpendicular
component of the flow over the surface
that's through the Sigma here that gives
us the total amount of fluid coming out
per unit time for example and that has
to be
the amount of fluid that's being
generated in the interior by the
divergence
this is Gauss's theorem the relationship
between the integral of the divergence
on the interior of some region and the
integral over the boundary where where
it's measuring the flux the amount of
stuff that's coming out through the
boundary fundamental theorem and let's
let's see what it says now any questions
about that Gauss's theorem here you'll
see how it works I'll show you how it
works yeah yeah you could have sure if
you had a compressible fluid you could
discover that all the fluid out boundary
here is all moving inwards in every
direction without any new fluid being
formed in fact what's happening is just
the fluid is getting squeezed but if the
fluid can't squeeze if you cannot
compress it then the only way that the
fluid could be flowing in is if it's
being removed somehow from the center if
it's being removed by by invisible pipes
that are carrying it all
so that means the divergence in the case
of water would be zero there was no
water coming it would be if there was a
source of the water divergence is the
same as a source source of water is the
source of new water coming in from
elsewhere is right so in the example
with the 2-dimensional lake the source
is water flowing in from underneath the
sink which is the negative of a source
is the water flowing out and in the
2-dimensional example this wouldn't be a
2-dimensional surface integral it would
be the integral in here equal to a one
dimensional surface and to go coming out
okay all right let me show you how you
use this let me show you how you use
this and what it has to do with what we
set up till now about gravity I think
hope a lifetime let's imagine that we
have a source it could be water but
let's take three dimensional case
there's a divergence of a vector field
let's say a there's a divergence of a
vector field del dot a and it's
concentrated in some region of space
that's a little sphere in some region of
space that has spherical symmetry in
other words doesn't mean it doesn't mean
that the that the divergence is uniform
over here but it means that it has the
symmetry of a sphere everything is
symmetrical with respect to rotations
let's suppose that there's a divergence
of the fluid okay now let's take and
it's restricted completely to be within
here it does it could be strong near the
center and weak near the outside or it
could be weakened near the center and
strong near the outside but a certain
total amount of fluid or certain total
divergence and integrated there vergence
is occurring with nice
Oracle shape okay let's see if we can
use that to figure out what the field
what the a field is there's a Dell dot a
in here and now let's see can we figure
out what the field is elsewhere outside
of here
so what we do is we draw a surface
around there we draw a surface around
there and now we're going to use Gauss's
theorem first of all let's look at the
left side the left side has the integral
of the divergence of the vector field
all right the vector field or the
divergence is completely restricted to
some finite sphere in here
what is incidentally for the flow case
for the fluid flow case what would be
the integral of the divergence does
anybody know if it really was a flue or
a flow of a fluid it'll be the total
amount of fluid that was flowing in per
unit time it would be the flow per unit
time that's coming through the system
but whatever it is this integral doesn't
depend on the radius of the sphere as
long as the sphere this outer sphere
here is bigger than this region why
because the integral over that there
vergence of a is entirely concentrated
in this region here and there's zero
divergence on the outside so first of
all the left hand side is independent of
the radius of this outer sphere as long
as the radius of the outer sphere is
bigger than this concentration of
divergence iya so it's a number
altogether it's a number let's call that
number M I'm not Evan let's just Q Q
that's the left hand side and it doesn't
depend on the radius on the other hand
what is the right hand side well there's
a flow going out and if everything is
nice and spherically symmetric then the
flow is going to go radially outward
it's going to be a pure radially outward
directed flow if the flow is spherically
symmetric radially outward direct
directed flow means that the flow is
perpendicular to the surface of the
sphere so the perpendicular component of
a is just a magnitude of AE
that's it it's just a magnitude of AE
and it's the same everywhere is on the
sphere why is it the same because
everything has spherical symmetry a
spherical symmetry the a that appears
here is constant over this whole sphere
so this integral is nothing but the
magnitude of a times the area of the
total sphere if I take an integral over
a surface a spherical surface like this
of something which doesn't depend on
where I am on the sphere then it's just
I can take this on the outside the
magnitude of the the magnitude of the
field and the integral D Sigma is just
the total surface area of the sphere
what's the total surface area of the
sphere just 4 PI 4 PI R squared oh yeah
4 PI R squared times the magnitude of
the field is equal to Q so look what we
have we have that the magnitude of the
field is equal to the total integrated
divergence divided by 4 pi the 4 pi is
the number times R squared does that
look familiar
it's a vector field it's pointed
radially outward
well it's point the radially outward if
the divergence is positive if the
divergence is positive its pointed
radially outward
and it's magnitude is one over R squared
it's exactly the gravitational field of
a point particle at the center here
that's why we have to put a direction in
here
you know this R hat this art will this R
over R is it's a unit vector pointing in
the radial direction it's a vector of
unit length pointing in the radial
direction right so it's quite clear from
the picture that the a field is pointing
radially outward that's what this says
over here in any case the magnitude of
the field that points radially outward
it has magnitude Q and it falls off like
1 over R squared exactly like the
Newtonian field of a point mass so a
point mass can be thought of as a
concentrated divergence of the
gravitational field right at the center
point mass the literal point mass can be
thought of as a concentrated
concentrated divergence of the
gravitational field concentrated in some
very very small little volume think of
it if you like you can think of the
gravitational field as the flow field or
the velocity field of a fluid that's
spreading out Oh incidentally of course
I've got the sign wrong here the real
gravitational acceleration points inward
which is an indication that this
divergence is negative the divergence is
more like a convergence sucking fluid in
so the Newtonian gravitational field is
isomorphic is mathematically equivalent
or mathematically similar to a flow
field to a flow of water or whatever
other fluid where it's all being sucked
out from a single point and as you can
see the velocity field itself or in this
case the the field the gravitational
field but the velocity field would go
like one over R squared that's a useful
analogy that is not to say that space is
a flow of anything it's a mathematical
analogy that's useful to understand the
one over R squared force law that it is
mathematically similar to a field of
velocity flow from a flow that's being
generated right at the center at a point
okay that's that's a useful observation
but notice something else supposing now
instead of having the flow concentrated
at the center here supposing the flow
was concentrated over a sphere which was
bigger but the same total amount of flow
it would not change the answer as long
as the total amount of flow is fixed the
way that it flows out through here is
also fixed this is Newton's theorem
Newton's theorem in the gravitational
context says that the gravitational
field of an object outside the object is
independent of whether the object is a
point mass at the center or whether it's
a spread out mass or there it's a spread
out mass this big as long as you're
outside the object and as long as the
object is spherically symmetric in other
words as long as the object is shaped
like a sphere and you're outside of it
on the outside of it outside of where
the mass distribution is
then the gravitational field of it
doesn't depend on whether it's a point
it's a spread out object whether it's
denser at the center and less dense at
the outside less dense in the inside
more dense on the outside all it depends
on is the total amount of mass the total
amount of mass is like the total amount
of flow through coming into the that
theorem is very fundamental and
important to thinking about gravity for
example supposing we are interested in
the motion of an object near the surface
of the earth but not so near that we can
make the flat space approximation let's
say at a distance two or three or one
and a half times the radius of the earth
well that object is attracted by this
point that's attracted by this point
that's attracted by that point it's
close to this point that's far from this
point that sounds like a hellish problem
to figure out what the gravitational
effect on this point is but know this
tells you the gravitational field is
exactly the same as if the same total
mass was concentrated right at the
center okay
that's Newton's theorem then it's
marvelous theorem it's a great piece of
luck for him because without it he
couldn't have couldn't have solved his
equations
he knew he meant but it may have been
essentially this argument I'm not sure
exactly what argument he made but he
knew that with the 1 over R squared
force law and only the one over R
squared force law wouldn't have been
truth was one of our cubes 1 over R to
the fourth 1 over R to the 7th with the
1 over R squared force law a spherical
distribution of mass behaves exactly as
if all the mass was concentrated right
at the center as long as you're outside
the mass so that's what made it possible
for Newton to to easily solve his own
equations that every object as long as
it's spherical
shape behaves as if it were appoint
appointments so if you're down in a mine
shaft that doesn't hold that's right but
that doesn't mean you can't figure out
what's going on you can't figure out
what's going on I don't think we'll do
it tonight it's a little too late but
yes we can work out what would happen in
the mine shaft but that's right it
doesn't hold it a mine shaft for example
supposing you dig a mine shaft right
down through the center of the earth
okay and now you get very close to the
center of the earth how much force do
you expect that we have pulling you
toward the center
not much certainly much less than if you
were than if all the mass will
concentrate a right at the center you
got the it's not even obvious which way
the force is but it is toward the center
but it's very small you displace away
from the centre of the earth a little
bit there's a tiny tiny little force
much much less than as if all the mass
was squashed toward the centre so right
you it doesn't work for that case
another interesting case is supposing
you have a shell of material to have a
shell of material think about a shell of
source fluid flowing in fluid is flowing
in from the outside onto this blackboard
and all the little pipes are arranged on
a circle like this what does the fluid
flow look like in different places well
the answer is on the outside it looks
exactly the same as if everything were
concentrated on the point but what about
in the interior what would you guess
nothing nothing everything is just
flowing out away from here and there's
no flow in here at all how could there
be which direction would it be in
so there's no flow in here so the
distance argument like if you're closer
to the surface of the inner shell yeah
wouldn't that be more force towards that
no you see you use Gauss's theorem let's
do count system Gauss's theorem says
okay let's take a shell the field the
integrated field coming out of that
shell is equal to the integrated
divergence in here but there is no
divergence in here so the net integrated
field coming out of zero no field on the
interior of the shell field on the
exterior of the show so the consequence
is that if you made a spherical shell of
material like that the interior would be
absolutely identical to what it what it
would be if there was no gravitating
material there at all on the other hand
on the outside you would have a field
which would be absolutely identical to
what happens at the center now there is
an analogue of this in the general
theory of relativity we'll get to it
basically what it says is the field of
anything as long as it's fairly
symmetric on the outside looks identical
to the field of a black hole I think
we're finished for tonight go over
divergence and all those Gauss's theorem
Gauss's theorem is central there would
be no gravity without Gauss's theorem
[Music]
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu